Guide to the Magie Dominic Off Off-Broadway Collection, 1952-2018 MSS.300
Fales Library and Special Collections
Magie Dominic Off Off-Broadway Collection
1948-2018
Fales Library and Special Collections
Dominic, Magie, 1944-
Gossage, James D.
MSS.300
10.25 Linear Feet in 7 binders, 3 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 1 oversize box, and 2 flat-file folders
Magie Dominic, an artist, poet, and founding member of the Off Off-Broadway theater movement, was born in Newfoundland in 1944, and resides primarily in New York. She founded and programmed the Children's History Theatre (1979-84), and was an active participant at Caffe Cino. The collection comprises materials created and compiled by Magie Dominic in the course of her involvement with the Off-Off Broadway theatre movement, especially Caffe Cino, as well as her own work as an artist and her work with the Children's History Theater. It includes clippings, photographic material, manuscripts, correspondence, and art and performance documentation.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Magie Dominic Off-Off Broadway Collection was donated to Fales Library by Magie Dominic in October 2010 and January 2011. An accretion was donated by Magie Dominic and James Gossage, September 2018. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.0124.
Arrangement
Series, folder and binder titles reflect Magie Dominic's original titles and arrangement. Small changes were made to facilitate access. Dominic's original order has been maintained; oversize and media items were removed from and placed in appropriate archival housing in separate series.
The collection is arranged into seven series:
Series I: Caffe Cino
Series II: Lost to AIDS
Series III: Ken Burgess
Series IV: Magie Dominic Art 1975-2011
Series V: The Children's History Theatre
Series VI: Media
Series VII: Data Storage
Biographical Note
Magie Dominic, an artist, poet, and founding member of the Off Off-Broadway theater movement, was born in Newfoundland in 1944, and resides primarily in New York. She founded and programmed the Children's History Theatre (1979-84), and was an active participant at Caffe Cino.
Source:
Dominic, Magie. "Dominic Magie L." Poets.ca. The League of Canadian Poets, 19 Apr. 2011. Web. 6 May 2013.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access copies for some materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Scope and Contents
This collection comprises materials created and compiled by Magie Dominic in the course of her involvement with the Off-Off Broadway theatre movement, especially Caffe Cino, as well as her own work as an artist and her work with the Children's History Theater. It includes clippings, photographic material, manuscripts, correspondence, and art and performance documentation.
Related Materials
Additional material can be found in the following archival collections:
New York Public Library Archives and Manuscripts, James Gossage photographs: http://archives.nypl.org/the/21426
Maggie Dominic Acker Award (MSS 488)
Off Off-Broadway theater.; AIDS (Disease) and art -- United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Photographs.; Posters.; Color negatives.; Color photographs.; Dominic, Magie, 1944-; Gossage, James D.; Ken, Burgess, 1935-1989 ((Kenneth Emerson)); Caffe Cino
- Series I: Caffe Cino, 239201
  Scope and Content
  Series I: Caffe Cino includes two binders of documentary files, including clippings and photographic material, as well as posters, related to Caffe Cino.
  - Caffe Cino Binder, 1952-81, undated; 239416 (Binder A)
  - Caffe Cino Binder, 1967-2010, undated; 239417 (Binder B)
  - Joe Cino Letter, 1948, 2018 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Caffe Cino and Its Legacy Exhibit Images, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 2-4)
- Series II: Lost to AIDS, 239202
  Series II: Lost to AIDS includes two binders of subject files compiled by Dominic related to friends and collaborators who died of AIDS, as well as documentation of the AIDS Memorial Quilt.
  - Lost to AIDS Binder, 1967-2008; 239419 (Binder C)
    Subjects include:
    Hibiscus, Eddie Bhartonn, Neil Flanagan, Seth Allen, Bill Haislip, Peter Hujar, Charles Ludlam, and Peter Hartman.
  - Lost to AIDS Binder, 1967-2008; 239420 (Binder D)
    Charles Lubier, Ken Burgess, Ken Hill, Tom Eyen, Johnny Dodd, Andy Milligan, and Victor LiPari.
  - AIDS Quilt Series, 1990, 1993; 239214 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series III: Ken Burgess, 239203
  Series III: Ken Burgess includes several coloring books designed by Burgess, as well as a binder of materials related to Burgess's work, compiled by Magie Dominic.
  - Coloring Book - "Animal Coloring Book", undated; 239253 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Coloring Book - "Coloring Book Cats", 1981; 239235 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Coloring Book - "Fantastic Original Art Birds", 1981; 239240 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Coloring Book - "Fantastic Original Art Cats", 1981; 239243 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Coloring Book - "Fantastic Original Art Dinosaur Era", 1981; 239245 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Coloring Book - "Fantastic Original Art Dinosaurs", 1981; 239246 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Coloring Book - "Fantastic Original Art Dogs", 1981; 239248 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Coloring Book - "Fantastic Original Art Egypt", 1981; 239249 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Coloring Book - "Fantastic Original Art Fantasy", 1981; 239250 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Magie Dominic's Ken Burgess Papers, 1973-90, undated; 239421 (Binder E)
- Series IV: Magie Dominic Art 1975-2011, 239204
  Series IV: Magie Dominic Art contains materials related to Magie Dominic's artistic output, including manuscripts, correspondence, and clippings.
  - Additional Essays + Village Voice Cover Story Illustration, 1999, 2001, 2003-2004; 239262 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American Theater Magazine, May 1992, 239270 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - ARC - The League of Canadian Poets Twenty-Five Years On; No. 26 Spring 1991, 239275 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Archie Comics Digest Magazine; No. 73, 1985; 239278 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Assorted Correspondence and Papers, 1989, 1993, 1995, 2005; 239281 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Chapbooks + Journals (Selected) [1 of 2], 1994-1998, 2004; 239284 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Chapbooks + Journals (Selected) [2 of 2], 1992, 1994, 1996-1997, 2009; 239288 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence w/ Margaret Atwood and Pres. Bill Clinton, 1994, 2008-2009; 239292 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence with Pope John Paul II, 1994; 239293 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence w/ Sister Joan Chittister, OSB, 1996, 1998-1999, 2002; 239297 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letters to the Editor, 1973-1974, 1991, 1999; 239299 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Literary Announcements, 1994, 1997, 2001; 239305 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Literary Correspondence, 1966, 1979, 1985, 1988, 1996-2005; 239313 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1996-1997, 2000, 2004; 239315 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1969, 1992; 239316 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - New York Times Poetry, 1985, 1990-1991; 239318 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The Queen of Peace Room [1 of 2], 2002-2005; 239322 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Queen of Peace Room [2 of 2], 2002-2005; 239324 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Queen of Peace Room" Preliminary Papers, 2002-2003; 239325 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Reviews, 1994, 2003-2004; 239327 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Symphony #4: Visions of a Wounded Earth, 1993-1994; 239329 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Teaching Workshops in Yukon, 2003, 239330 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Three Librettos, Correspondence w/ composer Bruce Patera, 2007-2008; 239333 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 'Village Voice', 'Toronto Globe and Mail" and 'Woodstock Times' Articles, 1975, 1999-2000, 2002; 239338 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "A Woman's Almanac", Voices from Newfoundland and Labrador, 1992; 239340 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Magie Dominic Art Binder, 1975-2011; 239422 (Binder F)
- Series V: The Children's History Theatre, 239205
  Series V: The Children's History Theatre documents the Children's History Theatre, which Magie Dominic founded and directed. Materials include correspondence, photographic material, clippings, and performance documentation.
  - The Children's History Theatre, 1978-84, undated; 239423 (Binder G)
- Series VI: Media, 239207
  Series VI: Media features audio and video materials from the collection.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access copies for some materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
  - Subseries A: Video recordings, 239208
    - "The Caffe Cino", WNET Television, October 7, 2007; ID: 300.0001; 243790 (Box 3, Media ID: 300.0001)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Original format: DVD-R
      Currently unavailable until duplication occurs.
    - "The Cockettes Are Coming", Theater for the New City, undated; ID: 300.0002; 243789 (Box 3, Media ID: 300.0002)
      Duration: 1 hour 5 minutes
    - Charles Stanley, undated; ID: 300.0003; 243791 (Box 3, Media ID: 300.0003, Case 300.0003)
      Existence and Location of Copies
      DVD access copy available.
      Currently available.
      Original format: 8mm film on VHS
      Color/No Sound
      Duration: 21 minutes
    - Summer Lightning, 2009; ID: 300.0004; 243792 (Box 3, Media ID: 300.0004)
      Original format: DVD
      Duration: 1 hour 40 minutes
  - Subseries B: Sound Recordings, 239210
    - Walt Disney's "Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs"; Walt Disney Productions, 1963; 243794 (Box 3)
      Original format: Sound Disc: Analog, 33 1/3 rpm; 12 in.
    - The Supremes, "More Hits by the Supremes"; Motown Record Corporation, 1965; 243793 (Box 3)
- Series VII: Data Storage, 243795
  Series VII: Data Storage contains two data storage discs from the collection.
  Born-digital materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
  - "Bob's Cino Page", undated; ID: 300.3.0005; 243797 (Box 3, Media ID: 300.3.0005)
    Format: CD-R
    Disc Label Annotations:
    "Use browser, view cinopage.html, master directory can be copied to hard drive"
  - "Cino Exhibit 1985", ID: 300.3.0006; 243796 (Box 3, Media ID: 300.3.0006)
    "Contains various images that include people - also XHN 33"
- Oversize Series I: Caffe Cino, 243777
  - "May Day" Poster, undated; 243778 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Laminated Caffe Cino and La Mama Posters, 1965-66, undated; 243779 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "The Talking Band: Poetry and Songs" Poster, undated; 243780 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Caffe Cino Poster, undated; 243781 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Oversize Series III: Ken Burgess, 243782
  - Greenwich Village News Clipping, undated; 243783 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Oversize Series IV: Magie Dominic Art 1975-2011, 243784
  - Magie Dominic Exhibition Poster, 1998; 243785 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Women Portray: 'Each One as She May'" Exhibition Poster, undated; 243786 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Collage, inspired by Ken Burgess, 1968; 275038 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Collage with hair and costume jewels, 1970; 275039 (Box 4, Folder 9)